<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Collonel Grey's portmanteau opened; his sealed, mis-directed, and returned letter discovered by a copie thereof, found among his other papers. Which is here printed and published with some queries and animadversions thereupon. To deliver, from the dangers of their caballs, such as are not acquainted with Scottish methods and mysteries.</title>
            <author>Colomiès, Paul, 1638-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E607_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205886</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865121</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865121</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80185)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E607[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Collonel Grey's portmanteau opened; his sealed, mis-directed, and returned letter discovered by a copie thereof, found among his other papers. Which is here printed and published with some queries and animadversions thereupon. To deliver, from the dangers of their caballs, such as are not acquainted with Scottish methods and mysteries.</title>
                  <author>Colomiès, Paul, 1638-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Du-gard, by the appointment of the Council of State,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 18th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Paul Colomiès.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Collonel GREY'S <hi>Portmanteau</hi> opened; His ſealed, miſ-directed, and returned LETTER diſcovered by a copie thereof, found among his other papers.</p>
            <p>Which is here Printed and publiſhed with ſome <hi>Queries</hi> and <hi>Animadverſions</hi> thereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To deliver, from the dangers of their Caballs, ſuch as are not acquainted with</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Methods and Myſteries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Du-gard,</hi> by the Appointment of the Council of <hi>State,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117358:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117358:2"/>
            <head>Colonell <hi>Grey's</hi> Portmanteau ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. His ſealed, miſ-directed, and returned Letter, diſcovered by a Copie thereof found among his other Papers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR that by a long Experience wee have been taught that the <hi>Scots</hi> never want their Inſtruments among us, and even of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, to make advantage of everie occurrence; And to repreſent all things (without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to truth) to the advantage of thoſe <hi>deſigns,</hi> to the promotion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they have baſelie and degenerouſly given up themſelvs, whereby thoſe, who have not leiſure or opportunitie to ſearch into affairs, or to take a view of their whole deſign, looking upon things by parts, and thoſe miſ-repreſented, are in danger to bee deceived, and drawn into actions of a nature that may bee dangerous unto them: It will perhaps bee held agreeable to the rules of charitie that they who underſtand theſe deſigns ſhould endeavor to undeceive thoſe, who do not, and to prevent that guilt and danger in which their ignorance may involv them, and out of which the rules of Juſtice and good Government (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in times of danger or juſt jealouſie) ought not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their good meaning to deliver them.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117358:3"/>
            <p>And to this end, for that it cannot but bee taken notice off, that a Meſſenger expreſs, hath been lately ſent from the Parlament of <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> bringing ſeveral Letters with him, whereof one was directed, <hi>For the Honorable</hi> William Lenthal <hi>Eſquire, Speaker of the Houſ of Commons in</hi> England. And for that there is no man known in <hi>England</hi> to whom that title doth agree, and therefore the Letter could not bee delivered; But may perhaps bee repreſented by their Inſtruments for other than it is, and well-meaning people abuſed by it, as if it were of another tendencie than it is;</p>
            <p>There beeing a Paper found among other Papers in the poſſeſſion of the ſaid Meſſenger, which had on the one ſide the Title aforeſaid (written by the hand of Sir <hi>John Cheiſlie,</hi> which is here verie well known) <hi>[Copie of the Parlaments Letter to the Speaker.]</hi> And within the ſame direction that was upon the ſealed Letter directed as aforeſaid, of the ſame Sir <hi>John Cheſlies</hi> hand, as the direction of the Letter it ſelf ſeem's alſo to bee. It is held neceſſarie to publiſh the ſame in Print, that all may ſee, what ſtuff it is, and to make ſome <hi>Obſervations</hi> upon it, to preſerv the well-meaning from miſtakes, and to make them warie how they ſwallow whatever they propine, they beeing ſeldom guiltie of much ingenuitie, or truth; but offer boldly what they think may ſerv their turn. By which if they reach their end, 'tis their clear gain. But if the effect bee a lie, as the means it ſelf is, it never coſt them a bluſh, that beeing the Index of ſuch a qualitie as is muſtered among the vices on the other ſide of <hi>Twede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 'tis probable they put more confidence in the Agencie of their Meſſenger, and his infuſions and negotiations with their partie here (who may perhaps ſhortlie burn their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers with ſuch traffick) then in what their Letter was like to effect, which they had reaſon to believ would never bee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, beeing ſo addreſsed as aforeſaid, whom they had there firſt furniſhed with this open Copie, and no doubt had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection what to do with it, for the publick cauſ of <hi>Scotland,</hi> though to avoid all further queſtions, the variouſneſs of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117358:3"/>which might have drawn from him (againſt his will) ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of truth, and made a diſcoverie of what it chieflie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern's them to conceal; Hee boldlie denie's hee had any ſuch Paper, and after 'twas ſhewed him, with confidence af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm's hee knew nothing of it, or that hee had anie ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which yet was found among Papers and Inſtructions which hee denied not to be his in his Port-manteau. This Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with his Comments on it, might have been ſufficient to deceiv many that know no more then what their Deceivers tell them. For prevention whereof, a care was taken hee ſhould have no converſ, but was defraied, while hee was here, and ſent back unto the Lord General, with a Meſſenger to attend him; who no doubt will ſend him into <hi>Scotland</hi> with a verie ſufficient guard. And give ſuch anſwer to the letter directed to him as will bee agreeable to the <hi>Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Parlament.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117358:4"/>
                  <head>A Copie of the Parliament's Letter of SCOTLAND to the <hi>Speaker.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Eſtaites of the Parliament of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, remembring that they haid wryten one letter unto you upon the ſext of <hi>March</hi> 1649, By ane expreſs vith inſtructiones for thair Commiſſioners then in <hi>Ingland,</hi> to bee comv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate to you, which did much concerne the good and peace of thes Kingdomes. And that they receaved one from you of the twantie third of <hi>Maie</hi> folloving, whairvnto they returned thair anſueyr upon the 26 of <hi>Juny</hi> 1649, and thairin took notice that they haid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved no returne to thairis of the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiding, naither have they to this day receaved any anſuer to the ſame, and having intelligence of the marching of your forcis towardis this Kingdome, and being certainly infermed that your ſhippes haue laitlie ſearched diueris, and ſeaſed upon ſome of the ſhippes with the perſones and guids thairin, belonging to this Natione, and conſidering how contrarie thes thinges are (whair thair hes been no provocatione vr injurie offred by the pairtie) to the Act of Pacificatione in the lairge Treatie, which requyre's That no ſhips ſould ſtope the Traide of the vther Kingdome, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117358:4"/>of Parliament, declairing a breach of peace, and iff any wrong be done, that vpon complaint and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance maide to the Parliament, or to thair Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioneris, redreſs and reparatione ſould bee ſought before it bee accompted a breach of peace by the whole Kingdome: And iff aither Parliament ſould denunce VVar, that they ſould give three months warning: They have thairfor reſolued to ſend, (as they do heirvith ſend unto you) authentick douplicattis of all thes four abovementionad Peapers: And to ſhow you that they keip the ſame principels, and reſolue ſtil to walk according to the ſame reulls and grounds, &amp; have no uther intentiones or reſolutiones, in relatione to Peace or War, in thes Nationes, then they did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs at large in thes Peaperis, as is moſt fullie ſet doune in thair Letter of the ſext of March, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructiones ſent thairwith to thair Commiſsioneris then in <hi>Ingland,</hi> whairin as they did then on thair pairt both ackowledge yair obligatione, and declair thair reſolutione to obſerue the reul of remonſtraiting, firſt the breaches of peace, of craving juſt reparatione, of uſing all fair meanis, of giving and preceiding warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of three monthis before ane Ingagement of thes Kingdomes in VVar; So they do now renew the ſame, and accordinglie have renewed the Acts of Poſtor and Leavie, for puting the Forcis of this Kingdome unto a readines, in caice of anie Invaſione, which were maid the laſt yeir, when they wreet thair forſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſext of March; All which they doe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnlie profeſs to be done by them in the ſinceritie of thair hairtis, not out of anie pollicie to catch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagis, for anie vther end or deſign guatſoever, but meirlie for thair awen defence, which they do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117358:5"/>aboundantlie ſufficient to remove al ground of jealouſies and maſs-reportis of thair intentiones, &amp; to tak away all pretence of neceſsitie of the marching of your Forcis, for the defence of the Borderis of <hi>Ing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> Whairfor on the the vther pairt, the Parliament being informed of ane reſolutione in <hi>Ingland</hi> to ſend an Armie to invade this Kingdome: They deſire to knove from you whether thoſs wha have the preſent power in <hi>England,</hi> doe acknowledge themſelvis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidged, or by thair anſuer will oblidge themſeluis, and declair thair reſolutiones to obſerue the forſaid way and ordor upon their pairt to us; and plainlie and cleirlie to declair unto us, whither thair Forcis doe march for defence, or offence, whether with intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones for keeping onlie within the borderis of <hi>Ingland,</hi> or for cuming within ours: which way of procedor in cleiring each otheris, and dealing plainlie, is not onelie agriabill to particular Treaties, and to the manie tyes, bondis and Declarationes paſt betwixt thes King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, but alſo to the Law of God, and practis of his people in his word, and to the comon Law and practis ewin of heathen Nationes; much more of Chriſtian Covenanted Kingdomes, and may prevent many evills and dangerus conſequencis which may fall out, even beyond and contrarie to the intentiones of Nationes, by thair Armies lying neir uther upon thair borderis, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho vpon meirlie intended defence. Hauing thus cleired thair intentiones, and deſired to bee cleired tutching yours</p>
                  <p>They further deſir, to let you know that as <hi>Jephtah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſent the lyk meſſage to the <hi>Amonites</hi> 2 <hi>Iudg.</hi> 12 and 27. So they reſt confident that the Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted God of thes Kingdomes, who did tak ordor with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117358:5"/>thoſe of this Natione, who unlawfully ingaged againſt <hi>Ingland</hi> 1648 doeth ſtill leive and regne, and will bring ſhame and rwine upon quhatſoeuer partie in ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thes Nationes that ſhall without ane neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie caus, and cleir calling, and without obſeruance of the Reull and ordor aforeſaid, of ſeeking firſt repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, and giving varning as aforeſaid, ſhall offend and invade the vther Natione. They further deſyr, That with this Bearer wha is ſent expreſs, ane anſuer may bee returned to this, and to the incloſed peaperis formerlie ſent unto yow, And that the ſubjectis of this Natione with thair ſhippes and guids may bee preſently releaſed and diſmiſſed. This is all that I have in command to repreſent to you from the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of this Kingdome, and reſtis</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>At <hi>Edenburgh</hi> 
                        <date>22 June 1650.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your humble ſervant</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>For the Honorable <hi>William Lenthal</hi> Eſquyre, Speaker of the Houſe of Comouns in <hi>Ingland.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117358:6"/>
            <p>If the <hi>Estates</hi> of the <hi>Parlament</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> would as well have remembred <hi>what</hi> they had written, as <hi>that</hi> they had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, perhaps they would not either have written <hi>now,</hi> or at leaſt not <hi>thus:</hi> If they would but reflect upon their letter of the 26 of <hi>June,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> here they mention, they might finde they had ſo declared an <hi>enmitie</hi> therein, that there was little reaſon to have urged thoſe Arguments which are conteined in this.</p>
            <p>That letter of theirs they will not complain ſure wanted an anſwer; for the Parlament gave one by a full Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion publiſhed <hi>Julii</hi> 14. 1649. w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is now again printed with their preſent <hi>Declaration, concerning the marching of their Armie into Scotland.</hi> Where may bee ſeen what that letter was, and what was ſaid to it, which wee have reaſon to believ was convincing (though no doubt they will not ſay 'twas ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorie) for they never gave word of replie, no more then they have to ſeveral others: and eſpecially they muſt bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain remembred, that to this day there want's an anſwer to the <hi>Parlaments Declaration</hi> of the of <hi>November</hi> 1646. a thing they have been often told of, but never had the heart to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it. For 'tis to bee obſerved as the conſtant <hi>practice</hi> of that Nation, to <hi>affirm boldly,</hi> and <hi>impoſe</hi> in their writings im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently, without all reſpect or reverence to truth, that there by they may take and carrie on, in their faction, ſuch as either cannot or will not examine them being that ſort of people, by whom they hope to do their work. But when their papers are anſwered, whether by a publick or private hand, they never yet adventured upon a <hi>Replie.</hi> And there is not one of all their <hi>papers</hi> of conſequence in all the controverſies they have moved about civil things, as well thoſe they printed, as thoſe they have ſent to the Parlament, but they have received anſwers which wee have reaſon to judg full; for that they have never either taken exceptions to the inſufficiencie, nor replied; but have given up their further pretenſions in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p>But whereas they ſeem to urge ſom wondrous ſalutife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Epiſtle of the 6 of <hi>March,</hi> which they could never have anſwer to; and would ſeem to inſinuate ſome rare preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117358:6"/>to bee there, for the good and peace of thoſe Kingdoms as they will needs call them, though one of them bee now more happie then to own the name: and complain heavily as they have don heretofore, that they could never get an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to it; Wee muſt tell them, that <hi>Epiſtle</hi> is <hi>Apocryphal.</hi> It lie's ſome where hid, and had ſure the ſame fate their laſt had, to bee never received. Certain it is, there is none ſuch to bee found among the Papers of the Parlament, and if it had com'n to hand, 'tis like enough to have had an anſwer, as well as any of the reſt: 'tis ten to one now this matter is obſolete, and too old to bee taken into conſideration. The contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies now are gon beyond <hi>paper-conflicts,</hi> and will bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by other Arguments. But that they may have ſom account of what is like to becom of that Letter, Wee ſhall deſire them to call to minde, That when their laſt Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, whom they mention, were in <hi>England,</hi> they ſent a paper to the Parlament the 14 of <hi>Februarie,</hi> 1648, which is alſo printed with this laſt Declaration, as it was alſo with the former, the later part whereof who ever ſhall read, will conceiv it a paper fitter to bee given in by a <hi>Herault,</hi> then <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners;</hi> and accordingly received a ſhort anſwer from the Parlament (there alſo printed) it not beeing capable of a longer. Upon the ſending of which their paper, They verie well knowing they had forfeited all priviledg of publick perſons, and had by that their paper of defiance merited an other kind of Treatment then they found, they ſecretly and clandeſtinely withdrew themſelvs without taking publick leav, as all publick perſons uſe to do, (hoping their paper would haue produced effects proportionable to its natural <hi>tendencie;</hi> and as affairs then ſtood, and as they by their ſecret infuſions among the people had prepared them, might have wrought ſom alterations amonſt us) and were about to ſhip themſelvs for <hi>Holland:</hi> But were again brought on ſhore, and ſent with a guard to <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſee whether the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> would <hi>own</hi> their miſcarriage, or <hi>puniſh</hi> it. But the Parlament <hi>owned</hi> what they had don. And ſo whether their Commiſſioners had inſtructions for what they did needs not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117358:7"/>bee enquired; for <hi>ex poſt facto</hi> the Parlament made it ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>particeps criminis.</hi> But they beeing taken into the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of the guard that carried them down upon the 6 or 7 of <hi>March,</hi> 1648. 'tis not poſſible thoſe inſtructions mentioned, or that letter could come to their hands till they were upon their waie homeward: By which means 'tis verie likely wee loſt the ſight of that Letter ſo much valued by them: how ever no ſuch thing is found exſtant, and therefore no wonder if it had no anſwer. And ſure now it will never have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of a publick one; but if it could bee found, it might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps bee examined by a private hand, to ſee what ſtuff it brought into <hi>England,</hi> and to what purpoſe. But the letter ſaith they have intelligence our <hi>Armie march toward that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and that our <hi>ſhips have ſearched ſom of theirs, and ſeized perſons and goods,</hi> &amp;c. And that <hi>theſe things are contrarie to the Act of Pacification,</hi> and the <hi>large Treatie, where there hath been no provocation,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis true, ſom of their ſhips have been ſearched and ſeized. What reaſon had they to exſpect other? do not they know they have been <hi>treating</hi> with the <hi>declared Enemie</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> whom they call their <hi>King?</hi> and do they not know, that having finiſhed their Treatie with him, hee vvas then everie daie exſpected there? and is ſince arrived? And can they think affairs here are ſo looſly mannaged, that vvee ſhould not ſee vvhat perſons and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are carried in their ſhips, eſpecially from <hi>Holland</hi> vvhere their <hi>King</hi> then vvas? And 'tis ten to one if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of theſe ſhips had found him there, they would have ſeized upon him too, if the conſideration, that <hi>'tis the greateſt miſchief may well befal you, to let him com amongſt you,</hi> had not adviſed the contrarie. But they need not ſtick much at this, for they are like to have more of it. And before this bee printed, the <hi>Armie</hi> is like not to have marched onelie <hi>toward</hi> their Kingdom, but <hi>into</hi> it. And by that time the ſound of their drums have avvakned you out of your dream, and you have conſidered things beeing well awake; you will finde that neither the one, nor the other, is either againſt the Act of Pacification, unleſs you could make your <hi>Parentheſis poſitive,</hi> which may bee taken to bee <hi>hypothetical.</hi> 'Tis true indeed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117358:7"/>there had been no <hi>provocation</hi> on your part, the thing had been under another conſideration. But whether there hath been a provocation or not, is out of queſtion to all, but your ſelvs; however wee exſpect you will ſay there hath not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſ the <hi>Genius Loci</hi> lead's you to affirm anie thing. And if wee had not been formerly ſufficiently acquainted with this kinde of ſtuff, it might have drawn forth ſom <hi>quaeries</hi> in an other dreſs then wee ſhal now put them. We would ask you,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What it is that you will call <hi>injurie</hi> when you are on the <hi>inferring</hi> ſide? for where you are <hi>paſsive,</hi> no doubt you know well enough.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What you will think to bee a ſufficient <hi>provocation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 3. If you bee awake, whether you have not indeed ſufficiently provoked the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by your late wicked invaſions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether you can think the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Pacification</hi> and the <hi>Large Treatie</hi> (which you mention) or anie Treatie at all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Nations bee in force, after the war begun by you, and this Nation invaded with a numerous Armie?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether you will denie there was anie <hi>Invaſion</hi> at all?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether this <hi>Invaſion</hi> was not made by <hi>decree</hi> of an <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Parlament</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Scotland?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parlament</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> do not <hi>binde</hi> and involv that Nation?</p>
            <p n="8">8. What thoſe <hi>provocations</hi> were, upon which your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland</hi> invaded <hi>England?</hi> and therein bee verie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that if you have not had, you may have an anſwer.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether there were not <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> from <hi>England</hi> with your Parlament (even when you were levying that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) for an <hi>amicable compoſure</hi> of all that might bee in difference between thoſe Nations.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether thoſe <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> were <hi>heard,</hi> or the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wherein they were inſtructed put into debate?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether the Treaties had anie <hi>reſervation</hi> of a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege for you to break them, when, and as often as you pleaſ; and that wee muſt bee bound by them notwithſtanding?</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether it was agreeable to the Treaties, that you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117358:8"/>ſhould garriſon and keep <hi>Barwick</hi> and <hi>Carliſle,</hi> Towns be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to this Common-wealth, which wee in conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the Treatie left ungarriſon'd.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether it were according to the Treatie and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that you ſhould invade <hi>England</hi> with an Armie?</p>
            <p n="14">14. Whether had you firſt ſought <hi>reparation</hi> and redreſs by anie complaint to the Parlament here, or to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners with you?</p>
            <p n="15">15. Whether you had denounced war, and given three moneths warning before your Invaſion?</p>
            <p n="16">16. Whether you were not unanimouſly agreed upon an Invaſion, but fell out among yourſelvs upon the point of Command, becauſe it was carried by <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and might not be under the direction of the <hi>Kirk,</hi> that is, four or five of their leading Prieſts?</p>
            <p n="17">17. Whether you think the two Nations have not been in a ſtate of hoſtilitie ever ſince your Invaſion?</p>
            <p n="18">18. How long forbearance of ſeeking juſt reparation ſhall make it unlawfull to ſeek it at all?</p>
            <p n="19">19. Whether the Parlament of <hi>England</hi> hath not given you ſufficient time to com to your ſelvs, and offer that which muſt bee had from you?</p>
            <p n="20">20. Whether they have not uſed all means, and made all fair offers of an amicable compoſure, even ſince the Nations have ſtood in a ſtate of hoſtilitie, and particularly by their Letter of 23 <hi>Maie</hi> 1649.</p>
            <p n="21">21. And laſtly, whether by your Letter of the 20 of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1649 you have not put things into an incapacitie of deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination by anie other waie then that of Arms.</p>
            <p>It might juſtlie make thoſe, that know you not, wonder to read your Letter; but to us there is nothing of that kinde ſeem's ſtrange. There is no man almoſt in either Nation, that take's notice of affairs, but know's, that when wee perceived you were gon off in your affections from the <hi>Parlament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for prevention of that evil they had cauſ enough to exſpect from you (ſeeing the Apoſtacie and corruption of your Commiſſioners here) ſent their <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> to your
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117358:8"/>
               <hi>Parlament</hi> into <hi>Scotland</hi> to compoſe all differences: but they were ſo far from effecting what was deſired, and the end of their miſſion, that they could never bring anie thing to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; But while they were ſtill there, notwithſtanding anie offers they had or might have had to propoſe, a war was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by their <hi>Parlament,</hi> and accordingly proſecuted to an Invaſion, without either <hi>cauſ</hi> ſhewed, or <hi>warning</hi> given, till <hi>Hamilton</hi> was entred into <hi>England:</hi> They garriſon'd our frontier-Towns, and went on committing all manner of acts of hoſtilitie, till it pleaſed our good God, who hath ever owned and carried on our cauſ, to appear for us and make an handfull of wearied men (who with very long marches had made haſte to expoſe their lives for the ſervice and ſafetie of their Countrie) his Inſtruments to chaſtize the pride and perſidie of that numerous and inſolent Enemie, who were wholly broken, and the greateſt part of them utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            <p>What provocation ſoëver they had for this Invaſion, which they never yet told us of, wee conceiv all indifferent men will beleev here was <hi>provocation</hi> enough to have drawn out a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>revenge,</hi> (which yet then was changed into a deep obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, had it met with men of the leaſt ſent of gratitude) and remain ſtill a ſufficient cauſe to require reparation. And wee verilie beleev there is no man that is maſter of common reaſon, or know's what belong's to civil tranſactions, or the rules of the common Law of Nations, but will without he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation bee bold to pronounce, That <hi>this Invaſion hath diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all Leagues and Treaties,</hi> and left this Common-wealth as free from all obligations or ſtipulations to the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as they are free from anie ſuch with the Kingdom of <hi>China</hi> or <hi>Iapan.</hi> And therefore to verie little purpoſe are thoſe Treaties and Acts mentioned, that have no beeing anie where in <hi>rerum naturâ,</hi> unleſs onely among the records of their guilt: where no doubt they will appear both to the Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and their own conſciences, when God ſhall make inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for that innocent blood that they ſhed while they brake and diſſolved them. Eſpecially wee may ſtand amazed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117358:9"/>at their <hi>impudence,</hi> that urge the beeing of them to us, which themſelvs moſt perfidiouſly broke without all or anie provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And 'tis an <hi>impudence</hi> alſo like theirs, to ſay they ſend the Copies of the firſt mentioned papers, to let us ſee they <hi>keep ſtill the ſame principles,</hi> and reſolv <hi>ſtill to walk according to the ſam rules and grounds,</hi> and have no other intentions or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, either in reſpect of war or peace, then is there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: When as the Parlament of <hi>England</hi> have clearly told them in a former Declaration, that by their Act they have left no ſuch rule in beieng, which yet they paſs over, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with as deep a ſilence as if they knew nothing of it, or as if by ſom <hi>Lethean</hi> draught their memories were becom <hi>abraſae tabulae,</hi> or by the power of ſom enchantment, or <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotick</hi> potion they had been faſt aſleep, while that ſcene was upon the ſtage. By this you may ſee the Letter was not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated for the Parlament, who (beſides that they knew well they would not open it) they knew muſt reſent with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme indignation their impudence in believing they could ſo impoſe upon them. But 'twas fitted for the vulgar, and for their proſelytes, who might perhaps bee brought to think that wee were ſtill under thoſe bands, and were about to break them, and to invade poor <hi>Scotland</hi> with an unjuſt war, in which there was nothing but abundance of candor, and a tender conſcientiouſneſs of the Treaties and Covenant.</p>
            <p>But they acknowledg their obligations by thoſe rules, and their reſolution not to invade without firſt uſing all fair means, and giving three moneths warning. As to their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, they ſhould do better to beſtow it upon their perfidie paſt, then uſe it to declare an opinion which they may as well change again as they have don before; and they may take it for their comfort, they do but <hi>ſing</hi> to the <hi>deaf;</hi> wee now know them too well to truſt them anie more under ſuch ſimple aſſurances as ſhall bee in their own power to break. As for their reſolution not to <hi>invade</hi> without <hi>three moneths warning,</hi> wee ſhall give no thanks to their good nature for that production; the ſtate of their affairs (which they are ever wont to bee moſt ruled by) at this time require it;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117358:9"/>They know not yet what to make of their <hi>King,</hi> and they had need ſee firſt how they ſhall bee able to <hi>mannage</hi> him, and ſee which way hee will incline, and whether hee bee like to prove an obedient ſon of the <hi>Kirk</hi> or not; if not, 'twill bee dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to raiſ an Armie for the <hi>invaſion</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> leaſt hee ſubdue the Kirk with it firſt. They ſee by their danger under <hi>Hamilton,</hi> that 'tis not ſafe to truſt Arms where they are not ſure of the Commanders. The Kirk find's they have had enough to do to mannage their little Armie there on foot this yeer to ſerv their turns; and they know the fortieth part of the Nation are not their devotiers, the reſt perfect <hi>Cavies,</hi> as wearie of their <hi>yoke</hi> for the burthen, as all good men are of their <hi>hypocriſie</hi> for the groſſneſs and <hi>formalitie:</hi> That if an Armie be raiſed of the Cavies they are loſt: That if their King ſhould humor them, and get them to engage againſt <hi>England,</hi> an impreſſion is not ſeaſonable with them till win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo they may have time enough to declare when wee think it time to leav the field. But then alſo, if they liſt ſo manie of their part, and ſend them into <hi>England,</hi> how ſhall the Kirk bee defended from their Malignant Partie at home? They are in ſtreights, and therefore troubled wee are ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and would have us believ their act of <hi>poſture</hi> and <hi>levie</hi> is onely for their <hi>own defence;</hi> which yet beeing made ſince their laſt invaſion, may argue there was then ſom little guilt awake that quickned their fear, that ſom account would bee taken of them for former injuries; for otherwiſe their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi> hath an intrinſecal fortification againſt all the Aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>ambition</hi> or <hi>avarice,</hi> and is as good a <hi>remedium</hi> of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended deſire, as <hi>deformitie</hi> is ſaid to bee of <hi>love.</hi> And this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their reſolutions they think is abundantly ſufficient to remove all ground of jealouſie and miſ-reports, and to take away all pretence of neceſſitie of the marching of our forces to defend the borders of <hi>England.</hi> Indeed wee cannot well bee of their minde, wee know not how ſoon the Lads may have a minde to bee upon Engliſh ground, which if they once feel under their feet, they'l ſhift for themſelvs at our charge. And wee wonder they ſhould think wee ſhould now
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117358:10"/>take their words, when they have ſo latelie broken their Treaties. Beſides, they know it no new thing for their Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to do it (witneſs among manie that ſignal one of <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth) though 'tis more then once they have paid dear for it, and may do now again before all accounts are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted.</p>
            <p>But you would fain know whether thoſe, who have the power in <hi>England,</hi> do acknowledg themſelvs obliged, or will oblige themſelvs &amp;c. That which will bee anſwer to this, there is no doubt but they will receiv before this can be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, from the <hi>Lord Generall</hi> of the <hi>Parlament</hi> of the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> in purſuance of the Declaration by them publiſhed: But for the expreſſion, what needs this liſping? you muſt ſpeak out before you get an anſwer to anie queſtion you will ask the General. Why <hi>thoſe who now have the power,</hi> why not the <hi>Parlament</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> that is their declared ſtyle in which they will bee addreſſed unto, and they will not bate you an hair of it. And what you mean by the <hi>power</hi> wee know not; but you maie take notice they have <hi>Autoritie</hi> as well as <hi>Power.</hi> Your own you can call a <hi>Parlament,</hi> and yet you might remember how it came to bee one. You know how your former <hi>Parlament</hi> was beaten up after the defeat of <hi>Hamilton;</hi> and this now in beeing cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen while the other was, and that by the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> forces then in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who in ſtead of <hi>puniſhing</hi> your paſt <hi>perfidie,</hi> gave you the <hi>power</hi> you have, and left you in a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to be ingratefull; which for bringing ſo ſignally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to act as you have don, they maie return to chaſtize you for it. The <hi>Parlament</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth of England</hi> is ſo, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you acknowledg it or no, and you maie chooſ whether you will or not; but if you have occaſion to ſend anie Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Meſſages that you will have received, you ſhall beſt conſult your own buſineſs if you give a right addreſs, they will otherwiſe ſpeed as well as Colonell <hi>Grey</hi> and the Letters brought by him have done. There needs no further anſwer to your repeated quaeres about obligation, or proceeding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Laws of Nations, to which you will receiv your
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117358:10"/>anſwer at home. And the Parliament's Declaration hath ſaid ſufficient for the JUSTICE, NECESSITIE, and ENDS of this <hi>Expedition;</hi> Wee ſhall onely tell you again, becauſ you ſtick ſo cloſe to it, that the Nations are not covenanted, and there is no ſuch thing in force. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that you need fear the inconveniences of the Armie's lying neer one another upon the borders; for the Engliſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie intend not to lie there, but to march into the bowels of your Countrie, and there take reparation, if it can be found, for all the ſpoils, plunders, and devaſtations by you made in <hi>England.</hi> And to make you underſtand how unthriving a courſ it is, bee your neceſſities never ſo great, to take up, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of Intereſt (without conſulting juſtice) at ſo great diſadvantage. Onely, to cloſe up all, wee muſt tell you, wee are not much edified with your apocryphal attribute of a <hi>[covenanted]</hi> God: And tell you that it is the <hi>mantle</hi> that hath vailed the groſſeſt <hi>hypocriſie</hi> that ever the ſun ſaw.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, the Divine Juſtice took order with them that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully, as you ſay, invaded <hi>England</hi> in the yeer 1648. And you muſt take notice, that it was the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> by the Autoritie of their Parlament, that invaded us. And you ſhould do well to conſider, what <hi>reparation</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath made to this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> for the injuries and wrongs don by them; or whether you think your nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal guilt bee ſufficiently expiated by expoſing ſom particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to the ſhame of your penitentiall Stool, or that the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> of <hi>England</hi> value's that hypocritical foolerie at ſo high a rate, as to accept it for the price of blood, or to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a ballancing reparation for all thoſe plunderings and devaſtations by them committed and made in <hi>England;</hi> or that you can, upon coming out of that Stool, ſo wipe your mouths, as you may truly ſay there remain's upon you neither guilt nor blemiſh of that wickedneſs: Or whether you think you can be able to impoſe upon the Divine Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſatisfie his juſtice with a few good words. You might do well to examine, whether the Lord may not yet have a controverſie againſt you for that unanimous reſolution
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117358:11"/>of the Invaſion of <hi>England,</hi> which is verie well known, was never called into queſtion among you upon the point of lawfulneſs, till the <hi>Kirk</hi> began to ſee that it would bee carried on, and mannaged by perſons who were not much devoted to their <hi>Intereſt.</hi> And they ſhall do well for a further diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie of their own deceit to ask themſelvs, whether they have not had ſince that ſom thoughts toward another Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Nation, in caſe their King ſhould prove to their minde, and they ſhould judg him worthie their ingaging for him. Bee not deceived, God is not mocked; conſider un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe Eies you are, and ſpeak your hearts, becauſ God ſee's them. Wee do acknowledg with an humble and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiall ſenſ, that the ſame Lord doth ſtill live and reign, and rejoyce that hee doth ſo; and are confident hee will diſcover and bring to ſhame and puniſhment too all thoſe that hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critically think to veil themſelvs from his All-ſeeing Eies with a few formalities of expreſſions. And as the juſtice of our Cauſ is ſo clearly evidenced by the Parlaments Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that none but themſelvs will believ wee offend; ſo with confidence wee exſpect the bleſſing of God upon us in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, which wee have not undertaken till after the uſe and offer of all other means, and a long exſpectation to ſee if at laſt they would take effect, and their rejection of them, have left us no other but this laſt remedie, and neceſſitated us to the uſe of Arms.</p>
            <p>Wee ſhall cloſe with your laſt clauſ, wherein <hi>Scoticâ fronte</hi> you require that your <hi>Ships</hi> and <hi>Goods</hi> taken, may bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <hi>reſtored</hi> and <hi>diſmiſſed.</hi> Wee ſhall ask you whether you have as conſcientiouſly reſtored all that plunder and ſpoil which your Armie ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> at your laſt <hi>Invaſion,</hi> when you came furniſhed with Baggage-boies, and Baggage-women to drive and carrie away into <hi>Scotland</hi> what ever was in their way in <hi>England;</hi> not ſparing the verie Wainſcot of the houſes, leaving where ever they came emptie fields and bare walls. To ſay nothing of your former plunders while you called your ſelvs <hi>Friends,</hi> and were in our pay; you ſhould firſt have made reſtitution of all this, and not onely for that, but for that too which you devour'd &amp; waſted here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you had demanded the reſtitution of your poor Ships. But
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117358:11"/>you will needs ſtill endeavor to impoſe upon the world with this <hi>miſtake;</hi> That this march of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armie is the beginning of the War, and that there ought to bee a publick denunciation now before any act of Hoſtilitie, as this Capture of your Ships ſeem's to be. Whereas all Leagues, Treaties, and Covenants between the Nations were broken by you, when that Nation by their Act of Parlament decree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Invaſion of <hi>England,</hi> and accordingly put it in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Then the War was begun, and the Nations have ever ſince been in a ſtate of Hoſtilitie: And if the Parlament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> did not then immediately, and ſo ever ſince continue and proſecute the ſame with fire and ſword, it hath not been, for that in juſtice by the Law of Nations they might not have don it, for they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not that juſtice but that they might give them time to reflect upon their wrong, &amp; how obnoxious they were to a juſt revenge; &amp; cool themſelves to a temper fit to receiv a meſſage for reparation; which if they had receiv'd with an acceptation becomming their guilt, and inſtead of the Paper of defiance of the 26 of June, returned an anſwer beecoming their guilt and weakneſs, there might perhaps have been an amicable compoſure notwithſtanding all their paſt wrongs. But while even by their laſt anſwer they continue to provoke, and will not accept of means of compoſure, they plainly keep on foot the War they had begun; and muſt impute it to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs that they have compell'd us into it: And inſtead of quarrelling the new taking of their ſhips, they ought to give us thanks wee began no ſooner. But that during all this time that the Nations have been in a ſtate of Hoſtilitie, Wee have rather waited to ſee if time would ſpend, or alter the humor, or that the paroxiſm would intermit, that they might com to themſelvs, and endeavor to prevent, what they had juſt cauſ to exſpect as the merit of their perfidious Invaſion, and their injudicious and petulant Papers. And let them not ſay, wee now begin a War which they began two years ſince, and have ever ſince continued.</p>
            <p>For their letter to the Lord General, vvee ſhall ſay nothing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117358:12"/>to that. Becauſe hee received it, and vvill no doubt ſend them an anſvver becoming him and them.</p>
            <p>Wee have no more upon this occaſion to ſay to the State; onely before vvee part a vvord or tvvo to the <hi>Kirk,</hi> upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their hypocritical paper printed at <hi>Edinburg</hi> 21 of <hi>Iune</hi> 1650 conteining the cauſes of a Publick and ſolemn hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, appointed by the general Commiſſion of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembie, to bee keeped through all the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this <hi>Kirk</hi> upon the laſt of <hi>Iune</hi> inſtant.</p>
            <p>And before wee com to examine the paper, wee would ask one queſtion or two about their Kirk o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Scotland:</hi> Firſt, what it is? (though perhaps a <hi>National Church</hi> is not found in the Scriptures,) But if they would depart from that term, and ſay the <hi>Churches</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> what they are? A <hi>Church</hi> for the matter of it is uſually ſaid to bee a <hi>Companie of Believers,</hi> hard to finde in <hi>Scotland</hi> in the uſual acceptation, unleſs you make their <hi>Prieſts</hi> the object, and then there are as manie as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes. Where the people are more captivated to their ſacred ſorrie dictates out of their publick Tub, then anie wiſe men among the Papiſts are to the determinations of the infallible Chair. And indeed by reaſon of the guilt and ignorance of thoſe wretchedly beclouded ſouls, and that ſuperſtition, in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the cunning craftineſs of their Prieſts hath involved them, they are more afraid of the Anathema of their Kirk, in what capacitie ſo ever congregated, eſpecially at the conſequence of it, the effects that follow upon the dreadful Horn; then anie Papiſt is at the fulminations of the Lateran, or the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of the ſecular Arm. And in the later the compoſition is eaſier, whereas in offences againſt the former, beſides that there is no rule of Commutation for the ſhameful <hi>ſtule,</hi> hee ſpeed's well that redeem's his diſobedience with half his <hi>gear.</hi> And they never want the Magiſtrate at their beck, who are willing enough to deſerv a diſpenſation with their ſaults, while they are ſeverely officious to keep the vulgar in their obedience to the Kirk.</p>
            <p>But in a word the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> is Mes <hi>Robert Douglas,</hi> Mes <hi>Robert Blaire,</hi> Mes <hi>Samuel Rhetorfort,</hi> Mes <hi>Patrick Gille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpie,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117358:12"/>and three or foure more, let moſt of their principal Prieſts, whoſe Dictates no mand are either examine or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict, without incurring the ſuſpition of Hereſie or Schiſm, and the danger of beeing cut off from the Communion of thoſe true beleevers, thoſe <hi>Muffti's</hi> watching with a ſpecial care to keep their <hi>Muſſulmans</hi> pure from the infection of the Sectaries.</p>
            <q>This Paper coming therefore from their Reverend <hi>Kirk,</hi> that is, from ſix or eight of their leading Prieſts, let us hear what it ſaie's, And onely trouble them with a few queſtions upon everie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</q>
            <div type="paper">
               <head>Cauſſes of a Publick and Solemn Humiliation appointed by the Commiſsion of the General Aſſemblie to bee keeped through all the Congregations of this Kirk, upon the laſt daie of <hi>June</hi> inſtant.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> 21 <hi>June</hi> 1650.</head>
               <p>THE LORD's diſpenſations have often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Land to Humiliation and Faſting, ſomtimes by fear of ſnares, ſomtimes by threatned violence: But the grounds of this hold's forth an eminent degree of both theſe, as a fruit of manie miſ-ſpent and abuſed ſolemn occaſions. And although wee have no cauſ to faint, or caſt away our confidence in anie difficultie, yet wee conceiv it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com's all the Lord's people throughout this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſeriouſly to bee humbled for theſe cauſſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing:</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117358:13"/>
               <p n="1">I. Firſt the great danger the Land and work of Reformation are into, by the ſudden and unexſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted approaching of the Sectarian Forces in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> Which as it is without all cauſ or provocation from us, and inconſiſtent with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God, in the Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and the Large Treatie betwixt the Nations, So except the Lord prevent it, it threaten's no leſs then the ruine of this Kingdom and obſtructing of the work of God within the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The preſent diſtreſſed Eſtate of the people of God in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> now groaning under the Tyrannie of that partie, which ſhould the more affect us, ſeeing, if providence do not otherwaies diſpoſe, ere long wee our ſelvs may bee brought to the like or worſ extremitie.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Beſide the danger wee are in from that partie in <hi>England,</hi> wee are not without the reach of hazard from the Malignant partie; whoſe inveterate malice againſt the Work of GOD hold's them on to purſue the ſame deſigns, hitherto by the bleſſing of God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. notwithſtanding all theſe imminent dangers, the Land lie's in ſecuritie, ignorance, profanitie and formalitie; little conſcience is made of the Oath of God in our Solemn Vows, the guiltineſs of ſhort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wherein, and the breaches whereof before the Lord plead's againſt Rulers, Miniſters, Souldiers, and people of all ſorts, beſide the great unthankfulneſs for mercies old and late, and the great abounding of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie ſo common in manie parts of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee are therefore to praie,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. That God would keep us from the danger of that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117358:13"/>proud partie now in Arms drawing towards our border, That wee may neither bee infected by their Errors, nor harmed by their Violence, and that hee would diſappoint all their deſigns againſt this Land and the work of God, and break their yokes from off the necks of his people in our neighbor. King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</item>
                     <item>II. That hee would purge the Land from profanitie, Malignancie and all other our ſins, ſtir up all ſorts to their dutie, direct and bleſs them in it, for the furtherance of his work, and defence of his people, and that hee may keep us ſtreight therein, that ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies get no advantage by our declining from the Covenant either to the right hand or to the left.</item>
                     <item>III. That hee would ſhew mercie to our King, and cauſ his wrath to ceaſ from his Father's houſ, and bleſs the labors of our Commiſſioners with him, in bringing that Treatie to ſuch a ſolid cloſe, as wee may bee keeped from ſin and ſnares, and hee ſo brought to his Throne, as may bee for the good of Religion and comfort of his people.</item>
                     <item>IV. That as hitherto the Lord has ever been for a defence to the Aſſemblies of his Kirk, ſo hee would bee pleaſed graciouſly to countenance this enſuing General Aſſemblie both in the gathering and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedour thereof.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſtie, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117358:14"/>
            <head>Preface,</head>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> WHether their faſting have not been often without anie great humiliation? Or, whether this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſavor much of it or not?</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Quere.</hi> Whether by the conſequence of all your ſolemn Faſts (which your ſelvs are compell'd to call miſpent and abuſed) you have anie reaſon to believ they came from a right Principle, were performed in a right manner, or arrived at a merciful acceptance?</p>
            <p>Whether the end of abſtinence from food, and all gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous apparel, and what ever might elicite Acts of Senſ with complacencie, bee not, that the ſoul beeing retired into it ſelf from all things that might diſtract it by the luſt of the Eies, the luſts of the fleſh, and the pride of life, it might with a ſerious and ſad reflexion view all its actions, diveſted now of thoſe attires and dreſſes, with which it was faſcinated in its election and proſecution of them. And make a ſevere judgement of them, and of it ſelf for them, and bearing their guilt with a tender ſenſ lie down with a deep and true humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, under that mightie hand, who onely is able to take awaie their guilt, avert their puniſhment, and prevent their recidivation? and who ever doth deeplie retire into himſelf, and make's an unreſerved ſelf-denial the gate by which, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv's there ſuch impreſſions, as are not eaſily delible. All the world maie ſee, by the effects, the <hi>Scots</hi> faſts are none of theſe. But the poor, ſillie, ignorant, ſuperſtitious people are brought together, under the thundering and ranting of the Lords of their Conſciences (who have their Theme given them from the General Aſſemblie, or High Commiſſion of the <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi>) that they may be wrought to a tempe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to receiv ſuch
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117358:14"/>impreſſions from them, as may fit them to ſerv ſuch turns as the State of their affairs from time to time ſhall require. This is a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> faſt; and the infection of this foul diſeaſ hath gotten more footing in <hi>England</hi> then Sectarianiſm hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto don in <hi>Scotland.</hi> But one queſtion more to your <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face:</hi> What is that eminent degree of a <hi>ſnare</hi> you are now under, is it not ſom one of your own ſeeking? Have you not wooed your own danger, and now know not how to avoid it? You would have a <hi>King</hi> like all other Nations, when, if you had pleaſed, you might have been free? And you would take <hi>One</hi> of that Familie who your ovvn paper take's notice of to bee under the vvrath of God? <hi>One</hi> that you knovv perfectlie hate's you, and ſcorn's your Church? <hi>One</hi> that you have diſobliged in the higheſt degree in executing his Commiſſioner? You cannot but knovv you have fourtie to one in <hi>Scotland,</hi> vvho, upon principles of profaneneſs, and Cavalieriſm, vvill take his part againſt you. You had an experience of the Presbyterians of <hi>Orkney</hi> and <hi>Caithneſſ</hi> their joining vvith and declaring for <hi>Montroſs,</hi> vvhat a temper your <hi>Kirk</hi> is of, and of hovv good proof even againſt a vveak temptation, that you maie vvell think you are in a ſnare and doubt vvhether another abuſed hypocritical faſt vvill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Cauſ,</hi> Upon this, Wee vvould ask you, Whether this vvord <hi>Sectarian</hi> might not have been left out vvith <hi>decorum</hi> in this your ſolemn preparation to your daie of Feaſt? Whether the people might not have met in as fit a temper for the true ends of a faſt vvithout it?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Upon what ground you call the Armie of the Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a Sectarian Armie? the term is verie general, and muſt ſignifie what you pleaſ. The <hi>Parlament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath told you in their <hi>Declaration</hi> what their Religion is that they are off, thoſe who deſire to <hi>Worſhip God in the Spirit, and rejoyce in the Lord Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>have no confidence in the fleſh.</hi> And wee have good reaſon to believ that there are in that Armie, that you call <hi>Sectaries,</hi> ten times more of that Religion then will bee found in all <hi>Scotland.</hi> If they have diſcovered ſuch dangerous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117358:15"/>errors as you ſeem to make a noiſ with, you ſhould give them in particulars; for on this ſide <hi>Twede</hi> 'tis grown obſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lete to <hi>believ as the Church believe's;</hi> no, though it bee the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe decrees wee cannot ſubſcribe as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Canons in all things all things to bee beelieved, leſt wee ſhould intrench upon the Prerogative of the Scriptures, which wee <hi>acknowledg</hi> to bee the <hi>rule, and deſire to practice up</hi> to it, and to follow no other. And therefore neither ſhall wee in matter of Manners, for avoiding of prophaneneſs, model our ſelvs to the converſation of their people, who perhaps in that point may not have atteined the higheſt Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And cercainlie thoſe they intend for <hi>Sectaries</hi> in the Armie are ſuch, as in <hi>humilitie</hi> and <hi>uprightneſs,</hi> wait upon God, who is no reſpecter of perſons, and ſeek direction from him, who beeing infinite goodneſs will diſpenſ himſelf in light to all who ſhall in that manner ſeek it from him, not daring to preſcribe or limit the ſhinings out of his infinite Beams, but to follow to what ever degrees of Light and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs hee ſhall pleaſ to lead unto, and not give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs to the circumſcribing dictates of anie ſort of men, what ever they may arrogate to themſelvs, or preſume of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their own meaſure. But perhaps this is put in in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of that Act of their General Aſſemblie, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand's all Miniſters to preach againſt the Sectaries under pain of cenſure, for which reaſon they will ſeldom miſs them in anie of their Sermons, though they go never ſo far out of their waie to meet them. And there is good reaſon the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſemblie ſhould by their example keep alive this lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable practice which they have commanded others, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ſhall let it paſs here, without further examination.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Querie,</hi> What work of Reformation that is, that is in ſo much danger by the approach of the Hereticks? Is it that needfull work of the Reformation of your Manners? 'Twere pittie that ſhould bee hindred; there is need enough it ſhould proceed; Swearing and Curſing is your natural dialect, and you have no better imbelliſhment of your Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage or Schemes of elegant ſpeaking than the frequent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertexture
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117358:15"/>of Oaths and Execrations. What <hi>uncleanneſs</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs</hi> is practis'd, may bee in ſom meaſure obſerved by a ſurvey of the Crouds which perpetually fill their <hi>Stool</hi> of <hi>Repentance;</hi> What Reformation there is in the matter of <hi>Lying</hi> ſo frequent with them heretofore as gave beeing to that Proverb <hi>(As falſe as a Scot)</hi> may bee ſeen in this Paper in this verie Paragraph, wherein though it bee the warning for a ſolemn addreſs to God, they dare ſay the approachof our Armie is without all provocation? What name is there for this ſtupiditie of forgetfulneſs or impudence? have you uſed your ſelvs to theſe formalities of <hi>Lying,</hi> that you have made it impoſſible to you to ſpeak <hi>Truth?</hi> for the inconſiſtencie of it with the <hi>Oath of God</hi> in the Solemn <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the <hi>Large Treatie,</hi> Wee muſt tell you, as often as you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it, there are none ſuch in beeing. You have perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, on your parts, and yet verie happilie for us diſſolved them all. And wee hope it will bee long enough ere you get us again involved.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Cauſ,</hi> Wee ſhould ask what that people of God in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> is, that are in ſuch diſtreſs, groaning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tyrannie, and who thoſe Tyrants? Are they thoſe in <hi>Ireland</hi> with whom your Nation there have held ſo good correſpondencie? How come's <hi>Ormond</hi> and <hi>Inchiquine,</hi> and the Popiſh Biſhop of <hi>Clogher</hi> to bee Saints in the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender? Beſides with what face can you talk of Tyranni? is the like Civil Tyrannie practiſed among anie Popiſh, or Reformed (except onely in <hi>France</hi>) that is practiſed among you, where the poor Countrie-men (whom their Lords ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor with the name of Vaſſals) have ſo m ch allowed them as may keep them alive to do further ſervice. And 'twere a work of Chriſtian mercie to manumit thoſe poor creatures, and let them taſte a little of the freedom that belong's to men; But for their Eccleſiaſtical Tyrannie, it want's an example elſ-where, and 'tis to bee hoped will never bee taken up for a pattern by anie others, nor laſt long where it is, beeing ſo extravagantly abominable.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Cauſ,</hi> 'Tis well you now ſee your danger. Pray look
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117358:16"/>how you came into it, <hi>Perditio tua ex te ô Scotia.</hi> Thou mightſt have been ſafe and wouldſt not; pride and deſire of <hi>Domination</hi> in thy Prieſts have undon thee. They have choſen to put the whole Land into the power of the Malignants; they fear ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the peoples eies ſhould bee enlightened with that truth which would diveſt them of their Un-evangelical power and juriſdiction. And you ſhould have don well to have put that uglie pride of yours into the Catalogue of the Cauſes of your <hi>Humilation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Cauſ,</hi> Everie one that know's your Land, will grant there is <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>prophaneneſs,</hi> and <hi>formalitie</hi> enough in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> little enough either of your <hi>Oath of God,</hi> or anie thing elſ; though that ſame thing of your Own, your Covenant, bee more in your mouths then anie elſ. By your <hi>unthankfulneſs</hi> perhaps you mean to men alſo, if you knew what that ſame thing of <hi>gratitude</hi> were, you might perhaps think where you had been deficient in it. As for the <hi>Sorcerie,</hi> you might do well to re-examine whether you had good grounds for all your terrible burnings: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there bee not a Sorcerie among you, that is not yet ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of. Remember that <hi>Balaam</hi> was frequent in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices when hee endeavored to curſ. Som ſay, <hi>Ignorance and malice make a man fit to bee a Witch:</hi> And that the vehement intention, and going forth of the ſoul, from malice with fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, is the formal act of Witchcraft, as it remain's in the Witch. Something looking ſuſpiciouſly toward ſuch a thing as this, may ſomtimes perhaps bee found in a Circle of three or four foot Diameter; but wee hope with as little ſucceſs as <hi>Balaam</hi> had.</p>
            <p>But your Catalogue ſeem's to com ſhort; I'le help your memories with one more, for your next, for this is paſt; and that is, that you will remember to bee humbled and aſhamed that your <hi>Catholicon</hi> [the <hi>Stool</hi>] ſhould not have been able to charm that drunken Devil among you that poſſeſſed ſuch numbers at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> at the firſt news of the arrival of your King. You have ſure a rare way of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving in <hi>Scotland:</hi> Or did not you of the Kirk think to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117358:16"/>your ſelvs in it till you knew whether hee would ſerv your turn or not, and ſo leſt it to them that had no other form for it in the Cavaleriſh Directorie, but that of healths. It is like to prove a happie buſineſs whoſe <hi>Auſpicia</hi> are ſacred with theſe <hi>Lyean</hi> Myſteries.</p>
            <p>To your directions to pray wee ſhall ſay little, they beeing generally but in purſuance of the ſaid Cauſes; yet ſhall ask you if it be not poſſible there may bee as much pride expreſſed in the firſt line of this firſt direction, as is to bee found in all that partie in Arms, that is now coming againſt you? Is this your manner to inſtruct your people to com ſolemnlie to ſeek God with ſpirits thus ſeaſoned? You have often made a great noiſ, calling out that there might bee but one <hi>Directorie</hi> for Worſhip in both Nations; and would you have us take up this? is this the divine thing that muſt bee obtruded upon all? Did their ſweetneſs and love, and their rendring good for your evil, when they were laſt with you, and delivered you from your enemies, and gave your Civil Power that bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it now hath, deſerv that language. What was the pride you found in them then? or why is this bitterneſs againſt them that hath ever ſince poſſeſt you? Is it becauſe you muſt needs hate them that over deſerv of you? or becauſ they ſet you that unprofitable pattern (as you account it) which you mean not to follow, of a Chriſtian and generous ſelf-denial. Leav out this unſavory expreſſion next time. Remember <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam's</hi> ſacrifices, his diſ-appointment, and his end. Wee ſhall trouble this Paper no further, but adviſe you when you <hi>emit</hi> another, to direct the people to acknowledg that groſs <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie</hi> that hath ever followed your Nation beyond others: That you are the moſt abominable <hi>hypocrites</hi> in the world, which all men elſ know, though you will not: That you are the <hi>blinde Leaders of the blinde,</hi> and that they that are led by you are in danger to bee deſtroyed. And remember that you are alwaies under the eies of the infinite all-ſeeing Spirit, whoſe truth and wiſdom is engaged to diſcover and puniſh your <hi>fourberie</hi> and <hi>impoſture</hi> in the view of the world.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
